- The
Speaker 1: Senator from Vermont. - Mr. President, you know Vermonters are frustrated. They're angry. They've seen the Congress
Speaker 2: unwilling, and able to do its job, keep the government running. They've seen the fact that we've passed, we've passed the budgets, we've passed a continuing resolution here in the Senate. In a small group,
in
Speaker 3: the House of Representatives, a small group of Republicans say, no, we have to have everything
we want
Speaker 1: or nothing. And that's why we see here in Washington, museums, national monuments barricaded.
But it's more than just
Speaker 5: that, Mr. President. This morning in the Judiciary Committee, we heard
from the
Speaker 5: Director of the National Security Agency that
Speaker 2: as each day goes by, the impact and jeopardy of a shutdown
to
Speaker 2: the safety and security of this country will increase.
And
Speaker 6: that's true.
And the true
Speaker 6: toll of this needless exercise is just beginning to be felt. Some decry federal spending as though it's some kind of a communicable disease. But millions of American families,
Speaker 2: Republicans, Democrats, Independents, rely on government-supported programs that provide the lifeline to keep them
going.
key
Speaker 2: nutrition programs, like the Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program. My state that supports
Speaker 6: 100,000 Vermonters. Another 1,600 children and families benefit from Head Start. They're the ones that are gonna create, run our jobs in the next generation. More than 117,000 seniors are on Medicare, 200,000 Vermonters in Medicaid. They don't know how long this is gonna continue,
But
Speaker 6: the shutdown is hurting in other areas, too. Buyers hoping to purchase a home with a loan from the Federal Housing Administration are being turned away. Can you imagine that ripple effect
when real estate
Speaker 6: is finally starting to pick back up?
And what
Speaker 6: they're saying is, oh, the economy, we worry about the economy. They're trying to kill the economy
by not
Speaker 6: letting Federal Housing Administration work.
In
Speaker 6: Vermont, 450 technicians of the National Guard were furloughed, just another hundred released from active orders. That financial effect, of course, but the national security effects are amazing.
In Vermont,
Speaker 6: we have a lot of agriculture. There's no one in the field or in the office at the Department of Agriculture. 200 USDA workers who, especially this time of year, are there to help Vermonters,
Speaker 6: they've been forced to close up shop as a result of the shutdown. WIC, the Supplemental Food Program for Pregnant
Women and
Speaker 6: Young Children, is 100% federally funded. But there's only two weeks of funding available in Vermont for the nearly 16,000 participants of the state. And we say in two weeks, "Sorry, child," or "Sorry, pregnant woman, we can't feed you." Can't just wait until we get our act together, but we're eating very well.
Speaker 6: We're eating very well, but could you go without food
for a
Speaker 6: few weeks because we have a few more press conferences and a few more photo ops? What will happen to them? Our Republican colleagues in the House won't say. They apparently don't
care. We
Speaker 6: heard from one office in Vermont, Rural Edge. They're building more affordable housing in St. Johnsbury, Vermont.
The time has
Speaker 6: come for them to pay the contractor.
Speaker 6: The money is there, but nobody is at the USDA office to authorize the payment. Work is likely to stop. People have to be laid off. Winter is going to come, and that time to construct this affordable housing
is lost.
Speaker 6: Federal agencies operate in 50 states. We know that. There's 40 of them in Vermont, from the Department of Homeland Security, the Postal Service, the Veterans Administration, Department of Defense, Department of Agriculture,
Speaker 6: of justice, that's 7,000 people in my little state. Nearly 1,000 of them reported to work on Tuesday to receive a
Speaker 2: furlough notice. They have families, they have mortgages,
Speaker 7: they have
Speaker 6: payments, they have medical expenses. And suddenly we said, oh, I'm sorry, we people here, the Republicans in the House representatives of a small segment of them,
Speaker 6: are saying we're making points
Speaker 7: for our supporters so tough for you don't you're not going to find an acceptable way to pay your
bills we but we want
Speaker 7: you to pay your
Speaker 2: bills we're just not going to pay ours
failing to fund
Speaker 8: the government doesn't simply mean federal workers are furloughed
no
Speaker 1: revenue streams
for the
Speaker 1: federal government
dry up
Speaker 1: Department of Education, nobody's there to collect under fault of student loans. Department of Justice, civil fraud investigations, litigation,
Speaker 8: false claims, fraud
cases, bring
Speaker 8: a lot of money to the government, they're
on hold.
Speaker 6: We can go back and forth with this ping-ponging and continuing resolution. Now we're told, oh, well, we'll do a bit by bit, agency by agency. Oh, come on. They really cared about having the government
going
Speaker 6: and pass the
Speaker 7: appropriations bills. Go to conference, let's know that we can do it without being filibustered here by some of their same supporters. Go to conference and vote 'em up or
Speaker 9: down. Then you'd fund the National Park Service, Environmental Protection Agency, Forest Service, and others. There is a clear
path forward. We
Speaker 5: open the government.
and
Speaker 5: then pass in conference appropriations bills in regular order. On the Treasury, the federal judiciary, District of Columbia,
and so on.
Speaker 5: The Democrats
Speaker 10: in the Senate passed a continuing resolution and fund all federal agencies. They give us time to consider things
Speaker 6: for the next six weeks.
Handful of
Speaker 6: partisans in the House of Representatives say no, we can't do it. But we're elected to make decisions here, not to do slogans.
This
Speaker 6: reminder, like so many others, is sick and tired of the politics as usual. Let's come
Speaker 2: to the table. Let's be grown-ups. Let's be grown-ups and do what we said we ran for office to do, not ask and send my
full statement
Speaker 2: to be made part of the record.
Speaker 11: Without objection.